Guide to Anglican Church of Congo Records
Yale University Divinity School Library
Anglican Church of Congo Records
1923-2002
RG 196
Yale University Divinity School Library
8
(19 boxes)
Correspondence, reports, and other collected material document the development of the Anglican Church of Congo, or Province de L'Eglise Anglicane Du Congo, which grew out of the Church Missionary Society work in Uganda, was part of the Province of Uganda, Burundi, Rwanda, and Zaire, and then was established as a separate entity in 1992. These records were photocopied or scanned in the Congo or Uganda and sent to the Yale Divinity Library for safekeeping,.
Province of the Anglican Church of Congo
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Photocopied and scanned records of the Anglican Church of Congo were sent to the Yale Divinity School Library in the mid 2000s because the original records were in danger of destruction due to war and other preservation difficulties. Emma Wild-Wood, who had done dissertation research on the Anglican Church of Congo donated some of the files and arranged for others to be photocopied and sent to the Divinity Library.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
The first missionary work of the Anglican Church in Congo started with Ugandan evangelist Apolo Kivebulaya who settled in Boga in 1896, in the sub-region of Ituri. After his death in 1933 the church spread through the sub-region of North Kivu. After the independence of Congo in 1960 the Anglican Church experienced a time of great expansion.
The first diocese, Boga-Zaire, was created in 1972, as part of the Province of Uganda, Burundi, Rwanda and Boga-Zaïre, with Philip Risdale as Bishop. A second diocese, Bukavu, was created in 1976 with Ndahura Bezaleri as Bishop. In 1980 the Province Francophone d'Afrique, Eglise de la Province de Burundi, Rwanda and Zaire was inaugurated with Nhadura Bezaleri as first Archbishop. The first Provincial Synod took place at Bukavu. Njojo Byankya was consecrated as second bishop of the Diocese of Boga-Zaire in 1980 when Philip Risdale retired. The Diocese of Kisangani was created in 1980 with Tibafa Mugera as Bishop.
In 1981 the Institut Supérior Théologique Anglican (ISThA) was established in Bukavu. Following the death of Ndahura Bezaleri in 1981 Njojo Byankya was elected Legal Representative of the Anglican Church and the administrative offices were transferred from Bukavu to Boga. Dirokpa Balufuga was consecrated as the second Bishop of Bukavu in 1982. and Ndandali Justin became the second Archbishop of the Province of Burundi, Rwanda, and Zaire.
In 1984 a fourth diocese was created, Shaba, with Mbona Kolini as Bishop. In 1987 ISThA transferred from Bukavu to Bunia. Samuel Sindamuka becamse the third Archbishop of the Province of Burundi, Rwanda and Zaire. In 1992 the Diocese of Nord Kivu was created wih Methusela Musubaho Munzenda as Bishop. On May 5, 1992, the Province of the Anglican Church of Congo was created with Njojo Byankya as Archbishop. It now has seven dioceses. As a member of the Church of Christ in Congo (Eglise du Christ) it is known as the Anglican Community.
Scope and Contents
These records are the result of a project to photocopy and scan documents held by the Anglican Church in Congo and send them to the Yale Divinity School Library for safekeeping. Due to political upheaval in Congo in the 2000s, it was felt with some urgency that church records should be copied and sent elsewhere. Emma Wild-Wood, who had done her doctoral work on the Anglican Church in Congo, made arrangements for materials to be photocopied and mailed to the Yale Divinity Library, as well as donating scanned files that she had gathered in her research. The records that arrived from the Congo had little organization or information about provenance, and most were in French or in African languages. The Yale Divinity Library staff has done its best to organize these records based on notes received with the material, letterhead information, and dates, but we are cognizant of the fragmentary and uneven nature of the files and their organization and description. Many of the files seem to document the work of Patrice Njojo Byankya, who was Bishop of Boga-Zaire and first Archbishop of the Province of he Anglican Church of Congo. We welcome any information that researchers may be able to provide to improve the description and organization of the files.
Series I, Prior to Formation, contains documentation from before 1972. These records document the formation of the Mboga Mission by the Church Missionary Society working from Uganda.
Series II, Diocesan Records, picks up from 1972 when the Diocese of Boga-Zaire was formed as part of the Province of Uganda, Burundi, Rwanda and Boga-Zaïre. Njojo Byankya was consecrated as second bishop of the Diocese of Boga-Zaire in 1980 but also served as Legal Representative of the Province and as of 1992 as the Archbishop of the Province of the Anglican Church of Zaire, so there is overlap between these "Diocesan Records" and the Provincial-level records of Series III. The dioceses of Boga-Zaire, Bukavu, Kisangani, and Nord Kivu are fairly well documented but there is little material from the other dioceses.
Series III, Provincial / National Records, covers the period 1972 through 2001. The first section relates to the Province of Uganda, Burundi, Rwanda and Boga-Zaïre and the Francophone Province of Burundi, Rwanda and Zaire. The second section documents the inauguration and early years of the Province of the Anglican Church of Congo. The third section relates to the Eglise du Christ au Congo / Communaute Anglicane. The Church of Christ in Congo or CCC (in French, Église du Christ au Congo or ECC), is a union of 62 Protestant denominations, in the Democratic Republic of the Congo. The Anglican Church of Congo is called the Anglican Community within the Church of Christ in Congo. Much of the material in this section has to do with educational work.
Series IV, Programs, gathers together material related to educational, medical, and other types of work, which was not organized in the diocesan or national church files. Of most interest in this series may be documentation of The Mothers' Union program.
Series V, Related Organizations, contains primarily correspondence with various organizations with which the Church in Congo had relationships for financial support or other programs.
Series VI, Collected Material, includes published and unpublished works related to the history of the Church as well as a Mashi-French vocabulary.
Arrangement
Series I, Prior to Formation, 1923-191
Series II, Diocesan Records, 1966-2002
Series III, Provincial / National Records, 1972-2001
Series IV, Programs, 1968-2002
Series V, Related Organizations, 1978-1999
Series VI, Collected Material, 1974-2001
Anglican Communion -- Congo (Democratic Republic); Province of the Anglican Church of Congo
- Prior to Formation, 1923-1971; Series I
  - Correspondence and reports, primarily from Bishop's House, Kampala, Uganda, 1923-1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and reports, incl. memorandum on proposed Mboga Mission, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and reports, primarily to/from C.M.S. Mboga, Bishop's House, Kampala, 1935-1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and reports, primarily to/from C.M.S. Mboga, Bishop's House, Kampala, 1943-1946 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and reports, primarily to/from C.M.S. Mboga, Bishop's House, Kampala, 1947-1951 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence and reports, primarily to/from C.M.S. Mboga, Bishop's House, Kampala, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and reports, primarily to/from C.M.S. Mboga, Bishop's House, Kampala, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and reports, incl memorandum re. Mboga Deanery - Congo Republic - Ruwenzori Diocese - Province of Uganda & Ruanda Urundi, 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence and reports, incl. Philip Risdale to/from Leslie Brown, Archbishop of Uganda and Ruanda-Urundi, Erica Sabiti, Bishop of Ruwenzori / Archbishop of Uganda and Ruanda-Urundi, 1962-1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence and reports, incl. Theodore Lewis and others to/from Erica Sabiti, Archibishop of Uganda, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Diocesan Records, 1966-2002; Series II
  - Diocese of Boga-Zaire
    - Correspondence /adminstrative files
      - Bishop Philip Risdale files
        - Official documents, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - Correspondence between Boga-Zaire and Bukavu, 1976 Jun - 1977 Sep (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - Correspondence between Boga-Zaire and Bukavu, 1977 Oct-1979 May (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - Correspondence, general, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Bishop P.B. Njojo files
        - Correspondence, 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 6)
        - Correspondence, 1987-1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        - Correspondence, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
        - Correspondence, 1992-1994 (Box 2, Folder 9)
        - Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
        - Correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 11)
        - Correspondence, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Diocesan Secretary / administrative files
        - Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 13)
        - Correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 14)
        - Correspondence - Diani Baguma, 1979-1982 (Box 2, Folder 15)
        - Correspondence - Diani Baguma, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        - Correspondence - Diani Baguma, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        - Correspondence - Diani Baguma, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
        - Correspondence - Diani Baguma, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 4)
        - Correspondence - Diani Baguma, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
        - Correspondence - Diani Baguma, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 6)
        - Correspondence - Diani Baguma, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 7)
        - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 8)
        - Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 9)
        - Correspondence, 1993-1995 (Box 3, Folder 10)
        - Correspondence, 1996-1997 (Box 3, Folder 11)
        - Correspondence, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 12)
        - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Other files
        - Correspondence re. Rev. Mukulungani, 1984-1987 (Box 3, Folder 14)
        - Correspondence and reports re. Archdeaconry of Aru, 1984-1988 (Box 3, Folder 15)
        - Correspondence and reports re. Archdeaconry of Aru, 1990s (Box 3, Folder 16)
        - Correspondence and reports re. Archdeaconry of Muiti, 1995-1999 (Box 3, Folder 17)
        - Correspondence with Kisangani, 1991-1995 (Box 4, Folder 1)
        - Correspondence with England, 1992-1996 (Box 4, Folder 2)
        - Correspondence re. Evangelization, 1990s (Box 4, Folder 3)
        - Correspondence re. SOMA Conference (Sharing of Ministries Abroad), 1991-1995 (Box 4, Folder 4)
        - Youth correspondence, 1990s (Box 4, Folder 5)
        - Correspondence with/about former missionaries, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 6)
        - Correspondence with/about former missionaries, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 7)
        - Correspondence with/about former missionaries, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 8)
        - Correspondence with/about former missionaries, 1990s (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Programs
      - Education, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Evangelism, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Medical, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Pygmy work, 1994-1998 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Liturgical calendar, 1992 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Theological education, 1990s (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Historical notes, 1974-1975, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Jeunesse de Chretienne Agape, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Reports and statistics
      - Reports /statistics, 1970s-1989 (Box 5, Folder 6-13)
      - Reports, Synod documentation, ca. 1990 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Reports / statistics, 1990-1992 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Reports / statistics, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Reports / statistics, 1995-1996 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Reports / statistics, 1997-1998, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Reports / statistics, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 6)
      - Reports / statistics, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Financial records
      - Financial records, budgets, 1990s (Box 6, Folder 8-13)
  - Diocese of Bukavu
    - Diocescan Synod records
      - 1st Synod, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - 2nd Synod, 1985 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - 3rd Synod, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - 4th Synod, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - 5th - 6th Synods, 1994, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence
      - Correspondence, 1975-1979 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence, 1980-1989 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence, 1990-1999 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence, 2000-2001 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Reports / documents
      - Reports / documents, 1976-1979 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Reports / documents, 1980-1985 (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Reports / documents, 1986-1989 (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Reports / documents, 1990-1995 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      - Reports / documents, 1996-1997 (Box 8, Folder 5)
      - Reports / documents, 1998-1999 (Box 8, Folder 6)
      - Reports / documents, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 7)
      - Reports / documents, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Diocese of Katanga
    - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Diocese of Kindu
    - Informational packet, ca. 2000 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Diocese of Kisangani
    - Correspondence
      - Correspondence, 1972-1982 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence, 1983-1986 (Box 8, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence, 1987-1990 (Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, 1991-2000 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Reports / documents
      - Reports / documents, 1966, 1969, 1974, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Reports / documents, 1980-1982 (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Reports / documents, 1983-1987 (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Reports / documents, 1988-1989 (Box 9, Folder 6)
      - Reports / documents, 1990-1996 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Diocese of Nord Kivu
    - Correspondence
      - Correspondence, 1990-1992 (Box 9, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 9, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, 1994-1997 (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence, 1998-2002 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Reports / documents
      - Reports / documents, 1976, 1978, 1982, 1985, 1986 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - Reports / documents, 1987-1990 (Box 9, Folder 13)
      - Reports / documents, 1992 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - Reports / documents, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Reports / documents, 1994 (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Reports / documents, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Reports / documents, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Reports / documents, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - Reports / documents, 1998-2001, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Provincial / National Records, 1972-2001; Series III
  - Province of Uganda, Burundi, Rwanda and Boga-Zaïre / Francophone Province of Burundi, Rwanda and Zaire
    - Correspondence, 1973-1987 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Reports / documents, 1972-1973 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Reports / documents, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Reports / documents, 1978 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Reports / documents, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Reports / documents, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Reports / documents, 1981-1983 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Reports / documents, 1987-1991 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Reports / documents, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Province of the Anglican Church of Zaire
    - Correspondence of Archbishop Njojo
      - Re. inauguration of the Anglican Province of Zaire, 1992 Jan-Mar (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - Re. inauguration of Province, 1992 Apr (Box 11, Folder 11)
      - Re. inauguration of Province, 1992 May-Jun (Box 11, Folder 12)
      - Re. inauguration of Province, 1992 Jul-Sep (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - Correspondence with Church of Uganda, 1991-1995 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Re. budgets and meetings, 1992 Oct -1995 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence with U.S. and London Commissaries, 1993-1996 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - Re. Overseas Bishoprics' Fund, 1994-1996 (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence with Shaba Diocese, 1994-1996 (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - Re. new Prayer Book, 1995 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - Re. centenary of Anglican Church in Zaire, 1995-1996 (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - Re. education of Abp. Njojo's son, 1995-1996 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Miscellaneous, 1994-2000 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence of Provincial Secretariat
      - Correspondence, 1992-1995 (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence, 1997-1999 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Reports / documents
      - Reports / documents, 1992-1993 (Box 12, Folder 13)
      - Reports / documents, 1994 (Box 12, Folder 14)
      - Reports / documents re. centenary, history of church, 1995-1996 (Box 12, Folder 15)
      - Reports / documents, 199 (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - Reports / documents, 1998, 2000, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Eglise du Christ au Congo / Communaute Anglicane
    - Kisangani correspondence, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence / reports re. education, 1975-1985 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence / reports re. education, 1986-1989 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence / reports re. education, 1990 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence / reports re. education, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence / reports re. education, 1992-1994 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence / reports re. education, 1995 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence / reports re. education, 1996 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence / reports re. education, 1997 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence / reports re. education, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence / reports re. education, 1999 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence - miscellaneous, 1989-2001 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Reports / documents, 1973-1979, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Reports / documents, 1982, 1986, 1987 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Reports / documents, 1990, 1991 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Reports /documents, 1998, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 4)
- Programs, 1968-2002
  - Education and Family
    - Departement des Femmes et Familles Communautaire, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Theological training, Boga-Zaire, 1975-1977 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Ecole Theologique St. Apolo, 1980s (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - incl. Institute Biblique, 1990s (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - incl. Theological Education by Extension, 1990-2001 (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Evangelism
    - Decade of Evangelism, 1994-1995 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Reports, 1980s-1990s (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Medical
    - Dossier Service Medical, 1970s (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Dossier Service Medical, 1980s (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Reports, 1980s-1990s (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, 1990s (Box 14, Folder 15)
  - The Mothers' Union
    - Correspondence, 1979-1982 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1987-1989 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1990 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1994-1995 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1996, 1999 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Reports / documents, 1968, 1979-1983 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Reports / documents, 1984-1989 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Reports / documents, 1990-1992 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - Reports / documents, 1993-1995 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Reports / documents, 1997, n.d. (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Prayer Book
    - New Swahili prayer book, 1992-1994 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Refugee Work
    - Dungu, 1991-1994 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Register of refugees, 1994 (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1995-1998 (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Seminars / projects
    - Seminar for Social Transformation, Bukava, 1990 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Appui a las commission Justice, Paix et Reconciliation de l'eglise Anlican do Goma, 2002 (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Related Organizations, 1978-1999
  - African Evangelistic Enterprise, 1984-1995 (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - African Pastors Fellowship, 1991-1993 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Anglican Church of Canada, 1994 (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - Anglican Consulative Council, 1995, 1996 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Church Missionary Society - Correspondence, 1994-1996 (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - Church Missionary Society - Funds for Education, 1994-1996 (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - Church Missionary Society - Re. changes in Overseas Regional Office, 1993 (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - Church Missionary Society - Re. youth programs, 1990-1993 (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - Church Missionary Society - Reports / documents, 1995, 1999 (Box 16, Folder 16)
  - Church Missionary Society of Australia, 1993-1996 (Box 16, Folder 17)
  - Church of England - Diocese of Oxford, 1992 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Church of England - St. Peter's Church, Conisbrough, 1994 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Council of Anglican Provinces of Africa, 1996 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Episcopal Church, U.S. - incl. re. United Thank Offering (UTO), grants, scholarships, 1979-1981 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Episcopal Church, U.S. - incl. re. Diana Witts, UTO grant for Kinshasa project, 1982-1984 (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Episcopal Church, U.S. - incl. re. UTO, grant for refugee work, 1985 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Episcopal Church, U.S. - incl. re. UTO grants, 1986-1987 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Episcopal Church, U.S. - incl. re. grant for Diocesan Centre, 1988-1989 (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Episcopal Church, U.S. - incl. re. UTO, correspondence with Commissary, 1990-1993 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Episcopal Church, U.S. - incl. re. UO grants, Overseas Leadership Training, 1995-1998 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Mid-Africa Ministry (CMS), 1993-1996 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Oxfam, 1978-1985 (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Tear Fund, 1989, 1991-1992 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Tear Fund, 1993 (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Tear Fund, 1994 (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Tear Fund, 1995-1996 (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Zaire Church Association, 1993-1996 (Box 17, Folder 17)
- Collected Material, 1974-2001
  - Booklet: Kwa Imani Apolo - Maisha Ya Apolo Kivebulaya, 1986 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Paper: Vas à Béthel, n.d. (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Thesis: L'Implantation de l'Eglise Anglicane et son Développement dans les Zones de Masisi-Rutshuru et Goma by Nkusi Sebujisho J. / Institute Superieur Anglican, Bukavu, 1984 (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Thesis: La Problematique des Rites Funeraires "Maombolezo" Chez les Anglicans de L'Archidiacone de Lukalakala au Maniema by Bilunga-Kasingilwa-Kakinga / Université Libre des Pays des Grands Lacs, Goma, 1994 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Thesis: L'Implantation de l'Anglicanisme au Zaire 1896-1972 by Ndahura Bezaleri / Université Nationale du Zaire, 1974 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Thesis: Liturgie Anglicane et Inculturation Hier, Aujourd'hui et Demain: Regard sur la Célébration Eucharistique en République Démocratique du Congo by Dirokpa Balufuga Fidèle / Université Laval, 2001 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Photocopied book: Essai de Vocabulaire Mashi - Français (2 volumes) / published by La Société des missionaires d'Afrique, n.d. (Box 19, Folder 1-2)